I don't recommend
many supplements,
but a regular, reliable source
of vitamin B12 is critical
for anyone on a
plant-based diet,
and its deficiency can cause
an array of symptoms.
Watch the video to find out
what the optimal B12 dose is.
"The Symptoms of Vitamin B12 Deficiency
and The Optimal Dosage for Adults"
In 1853, a bedridden vegetarian
was reported to experience
a remarkable recovery upon eating
meat. Probably didn't help he was
an opium addict, but he had
been doing that for a decade.
It was only after five years as a
vegetarian did he end up bedridden,
covered in bedsores,
but a little beef
and mutton and he was
eventually up and about.
Can't blame the poor guy, as this was
nearly a century before the discovery and
identification of vitamin B12, resulting
in just one of six separate Nobel prizes
awarded for teasing out its
structure and function.
One of the most dramatic events
in the history of medicine
was the curing of pernicious anemia,
a B12 deficiency disease, an otherwise
fatal disorder, with a special diet
centered around calf and beef liver.
Vitamin B12 levels start to drop
with months of cutting out meat.
Yes, there are all sorts of benefits
of adopting a more plant-based diet,
but underestimating the risk
of developing a B12 deficiency
nullifies the health benefits
of a vegetarian diet,
or even a diet centered
around plant foods
but contains meat only
a few times a week.
Even moderate amounts of animal
products may not be sufficient
to restore and maintain
adequate vitamin B12 function.
Vitamin B12 is not made by plants.
It's not made by animals either, but
rather microbes that blanket the earth.
We presumably used to get B12 drinking
out of a mountain stream or well water,
based on studies showing vegetarians in
developing countries who drink purified
water appear to be at higher risk. But
now we chlorinate the water supply
to kill off any bacteria. So we don't
get a lot of B12 in our water anymore;
we don't get a lot of cholera, either—
that's a good thing that we live
in such a nice sanitary modern world.
Vegetarians living in developing world
slums appear to have fewer B12 problems.
Basically, the more hygienic
our meals, the less B12 we get.
Our fellow great apes like gorillas get all
the B12 they need eating their own feces;
I prefer supplements.
Before getting into the nitty gritty of
how much to take, how frequently,
and which type is best, what are
the symptoms of B12 deficiency?
What aren't the symptoms
of B12 deficiency?
It's known as "The Great Masquerader."
It can cause everything from abdominal
distention and chronic diarrhea,
to shortness of breath and
swollen red painful feet.
It can also cause Parkinson's syndrome-
like symptoms, skin darkening
that resolved with supplementation, and
something I had never heard of before:
bilateral useless hand syndrome.
The many faces of B12 deficiency
include neurologic symptoms
such as numbness and tingling in
the hands and feet, muscle cramps,
dizziness, cognitive disturbances,
difficulty walking, erectile dysfunction,
as well as fatigue, and psychiatric
symptoms like depression,
and even psychosis. For example,
a 47-year-old woman with a 5-year
history of psychosis, treated
with antipsychotic drugs,
cognitively impaired,
reporting visual hallucinations,
until finally her mother revealed
that the patient was following
a strict vegan diet for 7 years.
She started B12 supplements,
and her symptoms went away.
Years of her life lost in a psychotic
haze, all apparently because
she didn't want to take a supplement.
But vitamin B12 supplementation
is mandatory for anyone
eating plant-based diets.
Becoming psychotic is bad, but hey,
better than falling into a coma,
not to mention suddenly going
blind with multiple organ failure,
all thanks to B12 vitamin
deficiency on a vegetarian diet.
Looking into his eyes, they
saw "exuberant haemorrhages."
He was bleeding into his eyes.
You don't have to be an
ophthalmologist to recognize
this is not what the back of your
eyes should probably look like.
Compared to non-vegetarians, those
removing meat from their diets
tend to have healthier body weights,
cholesterol, blood sugars,
blood pressures with
a lower mortality rate
due to ischemic heart disease,
the #1 killer of men and women.
However, underestimating the
importance of correct supplementation
of vitamin B12 can
nullify these beneﬁts.
Currently, the ofﬁcial position of
associations and governmental agencies
is categorical and unequivocal:
in the case of a vegetarian diet,
even if you eat eggs and dairy,
in fact, I would extend that to
flexitarians eating a few
servings of meat a week —
supplementation of
vitamin B12 is required.
Now, it’s not just
those eating plant-based
that should be concerned
about getting enough B12.
About one in three non-vegetarians
aren’t getting enough
for optimal health and that
may exceed half in women,
especially when they’re pregnant.
But this number could run
as high as nearly 9 out of 10
among those eating
strictly plant-based
and 10 out of 10
doing it long-term.
There are three groups of people
who should ensure they have a regular,
reliable source of vitamin B12
by supplementing their diet
with vitamin B12-fortified
foods or B12 supplements:
Those who’ve had bariatric surgery
(which can sometimes
impair absorption),
those eating plant-based diets,
and the more than a hundred million
Americans older than age 50.
Why can’t you get regularly tested
for signs of functional B12 deficiency,
like getting your homocysteine or
methylmalonic acid (MMA) level tested?
Though those are nearly always
elevated in cases of B12 deficiency,
there are rare cases of severe
B12 deficiency manifesting
with normal B12 levels in the blood,
normal MMA levels, and
normal homocysteine.
How do we know it was B12 deficiency?
Because within months of B12 treatment
they made a remarkable recovery.
So, best to just take it and
not wait for symptoms to arise.
The question is how
much and how often?
Some recommend a single dose
of 50 to 100 micrograms a day
or a thousand micrograms twice a week.
Others suggest 50 to
150 micrograms a day.
Some even recommend
500 micrograms a day.
It all depends on the target
levels you want in your body.
For those with normal absorption
capacity, meaning being under age 50
with an intact gastrointestinal
system and without diseases
like pernicious anemia,
we normally lose about
one microgram of vitamin B12 a day;
so that’s how much we have to
replace, on average, every day.
So, why is the Recommended Daily
Allowance 2.4 micrograms a day?
Well, we only absorb about
half of the tiny doses of the B12
we get in our diet; so, by eating
2.4 we can make sure we absorb
the one microgram
into our body to replace
the one microgram we’re
losing every day.
Taking larger doses,
like in supplement form,
an even smaller fraction is absorbed.
So, it might take a single
oral dose of 10 micrograms
to get that one microgram absorption.
But just 10 a day failed to
sufficiently lower homocysteine levels
to under 10 even after a year;
so, maybe we need to absorb
more than that 1.6 micrograms
every day for optimal health.
The current RDA is primarily
based on a 1958 study
that just looked at a
small number of patients
and only measured their blood counts.
Absorbing one microgram a
day may be enough to maintain
blood cell production,
but may not be sufficient
for all the other things
that vitamin B12 does.
“Based on the data of several
vitamin B12 status biomarkers studies,
”maybe the recommended intake
for most adults should be raised
to more like four, which is
what you see for example in Europe,
suggesting they want
people to absorb at least
two into their body every day.
In that case you’d need to
take more than 50 a day.
And, now we have data suggesting
getting seven a day may be even better.
So, if you wanted to
absorb 3.5 micrograms,
half of the intake that may
optimize functional B12 status,
how much would you need to
take in a single daily dose?
This chart isn’t granular enough,
but there’s a formula
you can use to calculate it.
U stands for uptake,
absorption into your body,
and D is your single daily dose.
To absorb 3.5, you’d theoretically
need to take a single daily dose
of about 225, which I round in
my recommendations to 250 a day.
Now, that’s just one of
three methods you can use.
A simpler and cheaper way is
to take a single dose a week.
If you want 3.5 in you a day,
then you’d want to get
at least 24.5 in you in a week.
To get that in a single dose
you’d have to theoretically take
about 2,600 which I round in
my recommendations to 2,500.
OK, but that’s theoretical.
Maybe you need even more?
On the contrary, a new study
showed you can get away with even less.
Just 50 a day (not 250), or
2,000 once a week, (not 2,500)
reliably bought blood levels up,
and more importantly,
normalized methylmalonic acid
and homocysteine levels
within a matter of months.
So, based on this new study, I dropped
my supplement recommendations
down to that 50 mcg a day or 2000 mcg a week.